Register of the Grand Duchess Ksenii͡a Aleksandrovna papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Original Diaries and Correspondence, 1916-1919 (Boxes 12-13)
  - Original diaries of Kseniia Aleksandrovna
    - 1917 August 24 - 1918 January 16 (Box-folder 12: 4)
    - 1918 January 17 - June 18 (Box-folder 12: 5)
    - 1918 June 19 - November 9 (Box-folder 12: 6)
    - 1918 November 10 - 1919 March 25 (Box-folder 12: 7)
  - Original correspondence between Kseniia Aleksandrovna and her brother Nicholas II, Emperor of Russia, 1917-1918 (Box-folder 13: 1)
    Box 13 may not be used without permission of the Archivist (use copies in Box 6).
  - Original letters from Nicholas II to his mother Mariia Feodorovna, 1916-1918 (Box-folder 13: 2)
    Box 13 may not be used without permission of the Archivist (use copies in Box 8).
- Photographs, undated (Photo file)
  2 drawings, 1 painting, 14 postcards, 83 prints, 6 prints of paintings
  - Depicting Vincent Cardinal; members of the Danish royal family; members of the Russian imperial family officers and men of the Russian army, as well as scenes of their activities in campaigns against Austrian troops during World War I, as well as the war's effect on lives, property, and the environment; scenes in Finland, including a monument to Alexander III; a cottage in France; HMS Marlborough as well as a silver bugle located on the ship; churches and other buildings in Russia; the tomb of Giulietta in Verona, Italy; and miscellaneous personalities and objects (Envelope A)
- Increment, 1894-1960 (Boxes 14-18)
  Biographical materials, correspondence, subject file, photographs, and postcards, arranged by physical form.
  - Biographical file
    - Greetings on Kseniia's marriage, 1894 January-July (Box-folder 14: 1)
    - Documents concerning the evacuation of Grand Duchess Kseniia from the Crimea on 11 April 1919 and then from Malta on 9 May 1919 (Box-folder 14: 2)
    - Correspondence
      - General, incoming
        - Unidentified, handwritten personal letters and greetings
          - 1900-1911 (Box-folder 14: 3)
          - 1922-1939 (Box-folder 14: 4-5)
          - 1940-1960 (Box-folder 14: 6-7)
        - Gadon, Vladimir, undated (Box-folder 14: 8)
        - Golitsyna, Ekaterina, undated (Box-folder 14: 9)
        - Nieroth, Georg, undated (Box-folder 14: 10)
        - ZHukovskii, M., 1894 January (Box-folder 14: 11)
        - Nestor, A., 1898 June (Box-folder 14: 12)
        - Suprunov, Fedor, 1904 January 11 (Box-folder 14: 13)
        - Belyi, Gerasim, 1906 December 12 (Box-folder 14: 14)
        - Kozakevich, Sergei, 1907 (Box-folder 14: 15)
        - Evreynoff, S., letters from Russia, 1917 January-December (Box-folder 14: 16)
        - Two letters contained in an envelope with the words "Letter, Count Sergei (D') Sheremetiev and Paul,", 1917 (Box-folder 14: 17)
        - Sablin, E., 1927 February (Box-folder 14: 18)
        - Kleinmikhel, Mary, 1929 January (Box-folder 14: 19)
        - Antonii, Archbishop of Kiev and Galitsiia, 1932 November (Box-folder 14: 20)
        - Mirskaia, S., Duchess, 1933 February (Box-folder 14: 21)
        - Sheremetiev, Dmitrii, 1936 July, undated (Box-folder 14: 22)
        - Kleinmichel, Vladimir, 1938 January (Box-folder 14: 23)
        - Levshin, Boris, 1939-1940 (Box-folder 14: 24)
        - TSeshkovskiy, E., 1940 April (Box-folder 14: 25)
        - Albright, Andrew, 1948 May (Box-folder 14: 26)
        - Ermakov, Mstoslav, 1954-1959 (Box-folder 14: 27)
        - Demchenko, Evgeni, 1955 (Box-folder 14: 28)
          Includes one photograph
        - Kamenski, V., 1956 (Box-folder 14: 29)
        - Rimarenko, Adrian, 1957 (Box-folder 14: 30)
        - Delianich, Ariadna, 1958 (Box-folder 14: 31)
        - Starikov, Simeon, 1959 April (Box-folder 14: 32)
      - Outgoing. Pavlova, Nastia, 1926-1930 (Box-folder 14: 33)
      - Family. Letters to Princess Kseniia from her son Nikita, daughter-in-law Marie (Vorontsov-Dashkov), and grandsons Aleksandr and Nikita
        - Sandro (Kseniia's future husband Aleksandr), 1889 August 4 (Box-folder 14: 34)
        - Telegrams and letters of condolence on the death of "Sandro" (Kseniia's husband Aleksandr) in France, 1933 (Box-folder 14: 35)
          Includes a letter from Princess Victoria of Wales.
        - Europe, including World War II, 1921-1955 (Box-folder 15: 1-4)
        - United States, 1940-1960 (Box-folder 15: 5-8)
          Includes six photographs
      - Royal relatives
        - General
          - United Kingdom, 1938-1958 (Box-folder 16: 1)
          - Sweden, 1941-1958 (Box-folder 16: 2)
          - Germany, 1950-1959 (Box-folder 16: 3)
            Includes two photographs
        - Georgii Aleksandrovich. Letter from Grand Duke of Russia (1871-1899) Georgii Aleksandrovich to his sister Grand Duchess Kseniia, Saint Petersburg, 1894 April 16 (Box-folder 16: 4)
        - Pavlova, Maria (daughter of Grand Duke Pavel Aleksandrovich), 1900 (Box-folder 16: 5)
        - Queen Olga of Greece, 1904, 1925 (Box-folder 16: 6)
        - Nikolai Nikolaevich, Grand Duke of Russia (1856-1929), 1920 July 10 (Box-folder 16: 7)
        - Prince Christopher of Greece, 1926 (Box-folder 16: 8)
        - King of Denmark, 1926-1948 (Box-folder 16: 9)
        - Prince George of Greece, 1926-1944 (Box-folder 16: 10)
        - Prince Aleksandr Romanoff, I, 1934-1959 (Box-folder 16: 11-12)
        - Prince Valdemar of Denmark, 1937-1938 (Box-folder 16: 13)
        - Princess Elizabeth of Greece, 1938-1956 (Box-folder 16: 14)
        - Princess Olga of Yugoslavia, 1938-1958 (Box-folder 16: 15)
          Includes one photograph, 1959
        - Prince Aleksandr Romanoff, II, 1943-1959 (Box-folder 16: 16-17, 17: 1-2)
          Includes postcard collection, 1928-1949
        - King Frederick IX of Denmark, 1958 (Box-folder 17: 3)
        - Princess Maria, Duchess of Kent, 1940-1959 (Box-folder 17: 4)
  - Subject file
    - Poem, glory to the Prince Nikolai, 1906 August 13 (Box-folder 17: 5)
    - Verses, some written by the hand of Grand Duchess Kseniia, undated (Box-folder 17: 6)
    - Material on death of Aleksander III, 1865 (Box-folder 17: 7)
      Includes essay "Moscow Mourns," poetry, and initiation from Count Petr Anrakhin.
    - Material regarding the last order of the Tsar Nikolai II from March 8 1917 (Box-folder 17: 8)
      Includes copy of the order.
    - Material regarding Anastasia case (Box-folder 17: 9)
      - Letters from P. Botkin, 1928
      - Letters from A. J. Wright, 1929
    - Letters to Aleksandr, with oversize materials (Box 18)
      - Duke Nikita Aleksandrovich, 1959
        Typescript
      - Duchess Maria Illarionovna, 1959
    - Nikita Romanoff, diploma, degree of Bachelor of Arts with a major in history, University of California, Berkeley, 1953 September 12 (Box 18)
      Photocopy. With oversize materials.
  - Religious materials
    - General, undated (Box-folder 17: 10)
    - Prayer, undated (Box-folder 17: 11)
    - Bible, New Testament, Saint Petersburg, 1905 (Box-folder 17: 12)
    - Photographs, undated (Box-folder 17: 13)
      Includes one print of Prince Aleksandr Romanoff (son of Prince Nikita), King Umberto of Italy, and Mother Martha; photograph taken in the grounds of Wilderness House, the home of Grand Duchess Kseniia - one of the only recorded photographs of Mother Martha, the companion of Grand Duchess Kseniia for many years. See also: correspondence.
    - Postcards - five Finnish postcards depicting Russian military personnel, undated (Box-folder 17: 14)
    - Miscellany (Box-folder 17: 15)
  - Oversize materials, 1910-1942 (Box 18)
    Original letters to Kseniia displayed in sleeves on oversize board. Dates given according to both the Julian and Gregorian calendars. The Julian calendar was in use in Russia until 1918, rather than the Gregorian calendar of the West. In the 20th century the former was thirteen days behind the latter.
    - Queen Olga of Greece (1851-1929)
      - 1910 February 19
      - 1914 December 27
      - 1917 July 31
      - 1917 September 27
      - 1923 January 16/29
      - 1923 March 19/23
      - 1923 March 24/April 6
      - 1923 April 11/24
    - Parting of the Empress Maria Fedorovna with her son Nikolas II, Emperor of Russia at the railway station, Saint Petersburg, 1917
      Written in September 1920.
    - Grand Duchess Ella (sister-in-law of Nikolas II, Emperor of Russia), 1912 February 26
      Includes photograph.
    - Victoria Melita, Grand Duchess of Russia (married to Kiril Vladimorovich)
      - 1917 August 6/15
      - 1918 July 13/26
      - 1918 October 9/22
      - 1919 August 15/28
      - 1920 November 13
    - Queen Maria of Romania
      - 1918 September 18
      - 1918 November 6/19
    - Princess Maria of Greece, 1919 February 24/March 9
    - Prince George of Greece, 1920 November 2
    - Letters from French Embassy in London and Belgium, permission allowing Kseniia take her bags through custom without hesitation, 1928, 1932
      Includes list and estimation of her jewelry in British pounds, 1929 May 22.
    - Gleb Botkin, 1928 October 18
    - Victoria Milford Haven, 1939 September 8
    - Princess Marina, Duchess of Kent, 1942 September 7